<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notes on Notes to self</title>
    <link>https://karecha.com/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notes on Notes to self</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 11:21:46 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://karecha.com/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Proactivity</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/09/18/proactivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 10:46:51 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/09/18/proactivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7_Habits_of_Highly_Effective_People&#34;&gt;The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People&lt;/a&gt;, the first
habit from the group &amp;ldquo;Private Victory&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;Be Proactive.&amp;rdquo;  Covey defines
proactivity so well that the answer to the question of how to be
proactive is almost self evident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By nature, humans are proactive.  If our lives are a function of
conditioning and conditions, it is because we have, by conscious
decision or by default, chosen to empower those things to control us.
In making such a choice, we become reactive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reactive people are often affected by their physical environment.  If
the weather is good, they feel good.  If it isn&amp;rsquo;t, it affects their
attitude and their performance.  Proactive people can carry their own
weather with them.  Whether it rains or shines makes no difference to
them.  They are value driven; and if their value is to produce good
quality work, it isn&amp;rsquo;t a function of whether the weather is conducive
to it or not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reactive people are also affected by their social environment, by the
&amp;ldquo;social weather.&amp;rdquo;  When people treat them well, they feel well; when
people don&amp;rsquo;t, they become defensive or protective.  Reactive people
build their emotional lives around the behavior of others, empowering
the weaknesses of other people to control them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to subordinate an impulse to a value is the essence of the
proactive person.  Reactive people are driven by feelings, by
circumstances, by conditions, by their environment.  Proactive people
are driven by values—carefully thought about, selected and
internalized values.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proactive people are still influenced by external stimuli, whether
physical, social, or psychological.  But their response to the
stimuli, conscious or unconscious, is a value-based choice or
response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Is Changing (Again)</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/06/28/software-is-changing-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 12:24:09 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/06/28/software-is-changing-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrej_Karpathy&#34;&gt;Andrej Karpathy&lt;/a&gt; recently gave a keynote at AI Startup School in San
Francisco and he called it &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LCEmiRjPEtQ&#34;&gt;Software Is Changing (Again)&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.  He laid
down the current state of AI/LLM assisted programming, and where it is
going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software development has evolved in these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software 1.0: code written by humans (started mid of last century)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software 2.0: programming neural nets with weights (started a couple of decades ago?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software 3.0: programming LLMs with prompts (started a couple of years ago)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karpathy advises anybody who is entering the field now to be good at all
of the above.  A good reminder for newcomers that 1.0 cannot be skipped
in spite of the current hype about AI which will make you believe that
learning to code is no longer necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other interesting tidbit is a new convention of adding llms.txt
along side your web documentation of whatever web services your company
offers, in order to enable coding agents.  For example, Stripe
documentation has an llms.txt at &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.stripe.com/llms.txt&#34;&gt;https://docs.stripe.com/llms.txt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote is worth watching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Links: 21 April 2025</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/04/21/three-good-links-21-april-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 09:58:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/04/21/three-good-links-21-april-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://endler.dev/2024/move-slow-and-fix-things/&#34;&gt;Move Slow and Fix Things&lt;/a&gt;: The author argues that moving slowly
doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t make quick decisions. It&amp;rsquo;s just that the
execution should be deliberate. Don&amp;rsquo;t wreak havoc along the way.
Because the time to fix what you might break rarely comes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://endler.dev/2025/best-programmers/&#34;&gt;The Best Programmers I Know&lt;/a&gt;: The author lists some important
traits of effective programmers.  For example, he says, the best keep
digging until they find the reason. They might not find the reason
immediately, they might never find it, but they never blame external
circumstances.  With this attitude, they are able to make incredible
progress and learn things that others fail to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://manuel.kiessling.net/2025/03/31/how-seasoned-developers-can-achieve-great-results-with-ai-coding-agents/&#34;&gt;Senior Developer Skills in the AI Age&lt;/a&gt;: Senior software engineers
are in the perfect position to ensure success with Coding Assistants,
because the very experience and accumulated know-how in software
engineering and project management best practices, which only seem
obsolete in the age of AI, are precisely what enable the most
effective use of these tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Links: 26 March 2025</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/03/26/three-good-links-26-march-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 09:39:41 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/03/26/three-good-links-26-march-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://trishagee.com/2025/01/23/staying-relevant-in-the-tech-industry/#more-2221&#34;&gt;Staying Relevant in the Tech Industry&lt;/a&gt;: Adaptability is key to
thriving in tech. This article explores strategies for staying
relevant, including continuous learning, embracing change, and
building a strong professional network to navigate the ever-evolving
industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://karpathy.bearblog.dev/digital-hygiene/&#34;&gt;Digital hygiene&lt;/a&gt;: This article on digital hygiene by Andrej
Karpathy explores practical tips for managing your online presence,
reducing digital clutter, and staying secure in an increasingly
connected world. It&amp;rsquo;s a blend of tech insights and actionable advice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc1180&#34;&gt;RFC 1180: A TCP/IP Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;: Dive into RFC 1180, a classic
tutorial on TCP/IP networking. This document breaks down the
essentials of how the internet works, covering protocols, addressing,
and routing in a clear, beginner-friendly way. A must-read for
networking pros and devs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Links: 27 Feb 2025</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/02/27/three-good-links-27-feb-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 08:20:52 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/02/27/three-good-links-27-feb-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.norvig.com/21-days.html&#34;&gt;Teach Yourself Programming in Ten Years&lt;/a&gt;: This timeless blog post
by Peter Norvig will continue to inspire software developers for
years to come. It translates well to any skill because the foundation
of effective learning is built upon the bedrock of being genuinely
interested in that skill and pursuing it because it&amp;rsquo;s fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.davefarley.net/?p=366&#34;&gt;Being a Technical Lead&lt;/a&gt;: New Technical Leaders have to quickly
learn some management skills, on the job, probably with no training
other than their previous experiences of see the impact that their
technical leaders had for good and bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mill-build.org/blog/8-what-is-a-build-tool.html&#34;&gt;What does a Build Tool do?&lt;/a&gt;: What does a build tool even do? This
blog post explores what build tools are all about, why they are
important to most software projects as they scale, and how they work
under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Links: 11 Feb 2025</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/02/11/three-good-links-11-feb-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 11:49:54 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/02/11/three-good-links-11-feb-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.davefarley.net/?p=360&#34;&gt;Team Topologies – Book Review&lt;/a&gt;: Dave Farley reviews the book
&amp;ldquo;Team Topologies&amp;rdquo; by Matthew Skelton and Manuel Pais.  This book adds
something important to our discipline: it defines an approach to
using organizational structure as a tool to achieve better results in
software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.digital-horror.com/blog/in-the-trenches-what-it-means-to-be-an-engineering-manager/&#34;&gt;What it Means to be an Engineering Manager&lt;/a&gt;: These reflections
offer one view into the realities and challenges of engineering
management, and may serve as a guide to those on a similar path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/02/03/deepseek-r1-do-we-need-less-compute-now/&#34;&gt;DeepSeek-R1: Do we need less compute now?&lt;/a&gt;: There is no
simplistic argument that faster algorithms and implementations
necessarily lead to lower spend on computing hardware.  History shows
that sometimes this is not true at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Links: 03 Feb 2025</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/02/03/three-good-links-03-feb-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 10:46:51 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2025/02/03/three-good-links-03-feb-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.bethcodes.com/code-review-heuristic-work-you-throw-away&#34;&gt;Pressure to Merge&lt;/a&gt;: How often does the team discard a set of
changes and go on to solve the problem a different way because of the
discussion in the code review?  The answer should be more often than
&amp;ldquo;never&amp;rdquo; and less often than &amp;ldquo;usually&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://martinfowler.com/articles/gen-ai-patterns/&#34;&gt;Emerging Patterns in Building GenAI Products&lt;/a&gt;: As we move
software products using generative AI technology from
proof-of-concepts into production systems, we are uncovering a range
of common patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://world.hey.com/jason/subjectivity-in-productivity-e0b4e2ee&#34;&gt;Subjectivity in productivity&lt;/a&gt;: Precision. Certainty. Specificity.
Everyone wants to know exactly what and exactly when, and they want a
statistic attached to corroborate it.  But numbers are rarely answers
— just as projects are rarely math problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Happiness by Pierre Teilhard</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/11/10/on-happiness-by-pierre-teilhard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 17:10:49 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/11/10/on-happiness-by-pierre-teilhard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Teilhard_de_Chardin&#34;&gt;Pierre Teilhard de Chardin&lt;/a&gt; delivered a lecture in Peking (now
Beijing) about happiness on 28 December 1943.  It was published as a
book by the name On Happiness, and is worth a read.  This book is now
hard to find and hence I am sharing the text below for the curious.
Note that he refers to Christianity a few times but if you replace that
with whatever faith you like, the text still remains relevant, at least
in my opinion.  It is a quick read and worth rereading every once in a
while.  Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REFLECTIONS ON HAPPINESS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Theoretical Axes of Happiness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Fundamental Rules of Happiness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;reflections-on-happiness&#34;&gt;Reflections on Happiness&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of mechanized matter, all bodies obey the laws of a
universal gravitation; similarly, in the world of vitalized matter, all
organized beings, even the very lowest, steer themselves and progress
towards that quarter in which the greatest measure of well-being is to
be found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might well imagine, then, that a speaker could hardly choose an
easier subject than happiness.  He is a living being addressing other
living beings, and he might well be pardoned for believing that his
audience contains none but such as are already in agreement with him and
are familiar with his ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, however, the task I have set myself today turns out to be
much nicer and more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all other animate beings, man, it is true, has an essential craving
for happiness.  In man, however, this fundamental demand assumes a new
and complicated form: for he is not simply a living being with greater
sensibility and greater vibratory power than other living beings.  By
virtue of his &amp;lsquo;hominization&amp;rsquo; he has become a reflective and critical
living being; and his gift of reflection brings with it two other
formidable properties, the power to perceive what may be possible, and
the power to foresee the future.  The emergence of this dual power is
sufficient to disturb and confuse the hitherto serene and consistent
ascent of life.  Perception of the possible, and awareness of the
future — when these two combine, they not only open up for us an
inexhaustible store of hopes and fears, but they also allow those hopes
and fears to range far afield in every direction.  Where the animal
seems to find no difficulties to obstruct its infallible progress
towards what will bring it satisfaction, man, on the other hand, cannot
take a single step in any direction without meeting a problem for which,
ever since he became man, he has constantly and unsuccessfully been
trying to find a final and universal solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;De vita beata&amp;rsquo;, in the ancient phrase — on the happy life: what, in
fact, is happiness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For centuries this has been the subject of endless books,
investigations, individual and collective experiments, one after
another; and, sad to relate, there has been complete failure to reach
unanimity.  For many of us, in the end, the only practical conclusion to
be drawn from the whole discussion is that it is useless to continue the
search.  Either the problem is insoluble — there is no true happiness in
this world — or there can be only an infinite number of particular
solutions — the problem itself defies solution.  Being happy is a matter
of personal taste.  You, for your part, like wine and good living.  I
prefer cars, poetry, or helping others.  &amp;lsquo;Liking is as unaccountable as
luck.&amp;rsquo;  You must often, I am sure, have heard that sort of remark, and
it may well be that you are a little inclined to agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I want to do this evening is to confront fairly and squarely this
relativist (and basically pessimist) skepticism shared by so many of our
contemporaries, by showing you that, even for man, the general direction
in which happiness lies is by no means so ill-defined as it is taken to
be: provided always that we confine our inquiry to the search for those
joys which are essential and, in so doing, take as our basis what we are
taught by science and biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot, unfortunately, give you happiness: but I do hope that I may be
able at least to help you to find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I have to say falls into two parts.  In the first, which will be
primarily theoretical, we shall try together to define the best route
leading to human happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second part, which will serve as a conclusion, we shall consider
how we must adapt our individual lives to these general axes which run
towards happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;1-the-theoretical-axes-of-happiness&#34;&gt;1. THE THEORETICAL AXES OF HAPPINESS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-the-root-of-the-problem-three-different-attitudes-to-life&#34;&gt;A. The Root of the Problem: Three Different Attitudes to Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are to understand more clearly how the problem of happiness
presents itself to us, and why we find ourselves at a loss when we meet
it, it is essential to start by taking a comprehensive view of the whole
position.  By this I mean that we must distinguish three fundamental
initial attitudes to life adopted by men as a matter of &lt;em&gt;fact&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here an analogy may well be a useful guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us imagine a party of tourists who have set out to climb a difficult
peak, and let us take a look at them some hours after they have started.
By this time we may suppose the party to be divided into three sorts of
elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some are regretting having left the inn.  The fatigue and risks involved
seem out of all proportion to the value of a successful climb.  They
decide to turn back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others are not sorry that they set out.  The sun is shining, and there
is a beautiful view.  But what is the point of climbing any higher?
Surely it is better to enjoy the mountain from here, in the open meadow
or deep in the wood.  And so they stretch out on the grass, or explore
the neighborhood until it is time for a picnic meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lastly there are the others, the real mountaineers, who keep their
eyes fixed on the peaks they have sworn to climb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tired — the hedonists — the enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three types of men: and, deep within our own selves, we hold the germ of
all three.  And, what is more, it is into these three types that the
mankind in which we live and move has always been divided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-first-the-tired-or-the-pessimists&#34;&gt;1. First, the Tired (or the Pessimists)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this first category of men, existence is a mistake or a failure.  We
do not fit in — and so the best thing we can do is, as gracefully as
possible, to retire from the game.  If this attitude is carried to its
extreme, and expressed in terms of a learned doctrinal system, it leads
in the end to the wisdom of the Hindus, according to which the universe
is an illusion and a prison — or to a pessimism such as Schopenhauer&amp;rsquo;s.
But, in a milder and commoner form, the same attitude emerges and can be
recognized in any number of practical decisions that are only too
familiar to you.  &amp;lsquo;What is the good of trying to find the answer?&amp;hellip;
Why not leave the savages to their savagery and the ignorant to their
ignorance?  What is the point of science?  What is the point of the
machine?  Is it not better to lie down than to stand up?  Better to be
dead than asleep in bed?&amp;rsquo;  And all this amounts to saying, at least by
implication, that it is better to be less than to be more — and that
best of all would be not to be at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-secondly-the-hedonists-or-pleasure-seekers&#34;&gt;2. Secondly, the Hedonists (or Pleasure-seekers)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For men of this second type, to be is certainly better than not to be.
But we must be careful to note that in this case &amp;rsquo;to be&amp;rsquo; has a special
meaning.  For the followers of this school, to be or to live does not
mean to act, but simply to take your fill of this present moment.  To
enjoy each moment and each thing, husbanding it jealously so that
nothing of it be allowed to be lost — and above all with no thought of
shifting one&amp;rsquo;s ground — that is what they mean by wisdom.  When we have
had enough, then we can lie back on the grass, or stretch our legs, or
look at the view from another spot.  And meanwhile, what is more, we
shall not rule out the possibility of turning back downhill.  We refuse,
however, to risk anything for the sake of or on the chance of the future
— unless, in an over-refinement of sensibility, danger incurred for its
own sake goes to our heads, whether it be in order to enjoy the thrill
of taking a chance or to feel the shuddering grip of fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our own version, in an over-simplified form, of the old pagan
hedonism found in the school of Epicurus.  In literary circles such has
recently been the tendency, at any rate, of a Paul Morand or a
Montherlant — or (and here it is far more subtle) of a Gide (the Gide of
&lt;em&gt;Fruits of the Earth&lt;/em&gt;), whose ideal of life is to drink without ever
quenching (rather, indeed, in such a way as to increase) one&amp;rsquo;s thirst —
and this with no idea of restoring one&amp;rsquo;s vigor, but simply from a desire
to drain, ever more avidly, each new source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-finally-the-enthusiasts&#34;&gt;3. Finally, the Enthusiasts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By these I mean those for whom living is an ascent and a discovery.  To
men in this third category, not only is it better to be than not to be,
but they are convinced that it is always possible — and the possibility
has a unique value — to attain a fuller measure of being.  For these
conquerors, enamored by the adventurous, being is inexhaustible — not in
Gide&amp;rsquo;s way, like a precious stone with innumerable facets which one can
never tire of turning round and round — but like a focus of warmth and
light to which one can always draw closer.  We may laugh at such men and
say that they are ingenuous, or we may find them tiresome; but at the
same time it is they who have made us what we are, and it is from them
that tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s earth is going to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pessimism and return to the past; enjoyment of the present moment; drive
towards the future.  There, as I was saying, we have three fundamental
attitudes to life.  Inevitably, therefore, we find ourselves back at the
very heart of our subject: a confrontation between three contrasting
forms of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-first-the-happiness-of-tranquility&#34;&gt;1. First, the Happiness of Tranquility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No worry, no risk, no effort.  Let us cut down our contacts, let us
restrict our needs, let us dim our lights, toughen our protective skin,
withdraw into our shell.  — The happy man is the man who attains a
minimum of thought, feeling and desire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-secondly-the-happiness-of-pleasure&#34;&gt;2. Secondly, the Happiness of Pleasure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static pleasure or, better still, pleasure that is constantly renewed.
The goal of life is not to act and create, but to make use of
opportunities.  And this again means less effort, or no more effort than
is needed to reach out for a clean glass or a fresh drink.  Lie back and
relax as much as possible, like a leaf drinking in the rays of the sun —
shift your position constantly so that you may feel more fully: that is
the recipe for happiness.  — The happy man is the man who can savor to
the highest degree the moment he holds in his hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-finally-the-happiness-of-growth&#34;&gt;3. Finally, the Happiness of Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this third point of view, happiness has no existence nor value in
itself, as an object which we can pursue and attain as such.  It is no
more than the sign, the effect, the reward (we might say) of
appropriately directed action: a by-product, as Aldous Huxley says
somewhere, of effort.  Modern hedonism is wrong, accordingly, in
suggesting that some sort of renewal of ourselves, no matter what form
it takes, is all that is needed for happiness.  Something more is
required, for no change brings happiness unless the way in which it is
effected involves an &lt;em&gt;ascent&lt;/em&gt;.  — The happy man is therefore the man
who, without any direct search for happiness, inevitably finds joy as an
added bonus in the act of forging ahead and attaining the fullness and
finality of his own self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness of tranquility, happiness of pleasure, and happiness of
development: we have only to look around us to see that at the level of
man it is between these three lines of progress that life hesitates and
its current is divided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it true, as we are so often told, that our choice is determined only
by the dictates of individual taste and temperament?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or is the contrary true?  That somewhere we can find a reason,
indisputable because objective, for deciding that one of these three
roads is absolutely the best, and is therefore the only road which can
lead us to real happiness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;b-the-answer-given-by-the-facts&#34;&gt;B. The Answer Given by the Facts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-general-solution-fuller-consciousness-as-the-goal&#34;&gt;1. General Solution: Fuller Consciousness as the Goal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my part, I am absolutely convinced that such a criterion,
indisputable and objective, does exist — and that it is not mysterious
and hidden away but lies open for all to see.  I hold, too, that in
order to see it all we have to do is to look around and examine nature
in the light of the most recent achievements of physics and biology — in
the light, that is, of our new ideas about the great phenomenon of
evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time has come, as you must know, when nobody any longer retains any
serious doubts about this: the universe is not &amp;lsquo;ontologically&amp;rsquo; fixed —
in the very depths of its entire mass it has from the beginning of time
been moving in two great opposing currents.  One of these carries matter
towards states of extreme disintegration; the other leads to the
building up of organic units, the higher types of which are of
astronomical complexity and form what we call the &amp;rsquo;living world&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being so, let us consider the second of these two currents, the
current of life, to which we belong.  For a century or more, scientists,
while admitting the reality of a biological evolution, have been
debating whether the movement in which we are caught up is no more than a
sort of vortex, revolving in a closed circle; or whether it corresponds
to a clearly defined drift, which carries the animate portion of the
world towards some specific higher state.  There is today almost
unanimous agreement that it is the second of these hypotheses which
would appear undoubtedly to correspond to reality.  Life does not
develop complexity without laws, simply by chance.  Whether we consider
it as a whole or in detail, by examining organic beings, it progresses
methodically and irreversibly towards ever higher states of
consciousness.  Thus the final, and quite recent, appearance of man on
the earth is only the logical and consistent result of a process whose
first stages were already initiated at the very origins of our planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, life (which means in fact the universe itself, considered
in its most active portion) is a rise of consciousness.  How this
proposition directly affects our interior attitudes and ways of behavior
must, I suggest, be immediately apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talk endlessly, as I was saying a moment ago, about what is the best
attitude to adopt when we are confronted by our own lives.  Yet, when we
talk in this way, are we not like a passenger in the Paris to Marseilles
express who is still wondering whether he ought to be traveling north
or south?  We go on debating the point: but to what purpose, since the
decision has already been taken without reference to ourselves, and here
we are on board the train?  For more than four hundred million years, on
this earth of ours (or it would be more correct today, since the
beginning of time, in the universe), the vast mass of beings of which we
form a part has been tenaciously and tirelessly climbing towards a
fuller measure of freedom, of sensibility, or inner vision.  And are we
still wondering whither we should be bound?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that the shadow of the false problems vanishes in the light
of the great cosmic laws.  Unless we are to be guilty of a physical
contradiction (unless, that is, we deny everything that we are and
everything that has made us what we are) we are all obliged, each of us
on his own account, to accept the primordial choice which is built into
the world of which we are the reflective elements.  If we withdraw in
order to diminish our being, and if we stand still to enjoy what we
have, in each case we find that the attempt to run counter to the
universal stream is illogical and impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road to the left, then, and the road to the right are both closed:
the only way out is straight ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientifically and objectively, only one answer can be made to the
demands of life: the advance of progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In consequence, and again scientifically and objectively, the only true
happiness is the happiness we have described as the happiness of growth
and movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we want to be happy, as the world is happy, and with the world?  Then
we must let the tired and the pessimists lag behind.  We must let the
hedonists take their homely ease, lounging on the grassy slope, while we
ourselves boldly join the group of those who are ready to dare the climb
to the topmost peak.  Press on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, to have chosen the climb is not enough.  We have still to make
sure of the right path.  To get up on our feet ready for the start is
well enough.  But, if we are to have a successful and enjoyable climb,
which is the best route?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, if we are to be sure of our ground, we must see how nature
proceeds — we must learn from the sciences of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-detailed-solution-the-three-phases-of-personalization&#34;&gt;2. Detailed Solution: the Three Phases of Personalization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, life in the world continually rises towards greater
consciousness, proportionate to greater complexity — as though the
increasing complexity of organisms had the effect of deepening the
center of their being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us consider, then, how this advance towards the highest unity
actually works out in detail; and, for the sake of clarity and
simplicity, let us confine ourselves to the case of man — man, who is
physically the highest of all living beings and the one best known to
us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we examine the process of our inner unification, that is to say of
our personalization, we can distinguish three allied and successive
stages, or steps, or movements.  If man is to be fully himself and fully
living, he must, (1) be centered upon himself; (2) be &amp;lsquo;de-centered&amp;rsquo; upon
&amp;rsquo;the other&amp;rsquo;; (3) be super-centered upon a being greater then himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must define and explain in turn these three forward movements, with
which (since happiness, we have decided, is an effect of growth) three
forms of attaining happiness must correspond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;em&gt;centration&lt;/em&gt;.  Not only physically, but intellectually and
morally too, man is man only if he cultivates himself — and that does
not mean simply up to the age of twenty&amp;hellip;  If we are to be fully
ourselves we must therefore work all our lives at our organic
development: by which I mean that we must constantly introduce more
order and more unity into our ideas, our feelings and our behavior.
In this lies the whole program of action, and the whole value and
meaning (all the hard work, too!) of our interior life, with its
inevitable drive towards things that are ever-increasingly spiritual
and elevated.  During this first phase each of us has to take up
again and repeat, working on his own account, the general labor of
life.  Being is in the first place making and finding one&amp;rsquo;s own self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, &lt;em&gt;decentration&lt;/em&gt;.  An elementary temptation or illusion lies
in wait for the reflective center which each one of us nurses deep
inside him.  It is present from the very birth of that center; and it
consists in fancying that in order to grow greater each of us should
withdraw into the isolation of his own self, and egoistically pursue
in himself alone the work, peculiar to him, of his own fulfillment:
that we must cut ourselves off from others, or translate everything
into terms of ourselves.  However, there is not just one single man
on the earth.  That there are, on the contrary, and necessarily must
be, myriads and myriads at the same time is only too obvious.  And
yet, when we look at that fact in the general context of physics, it
takes on a cardinal importance — for it means, quite simply, this:
that, however individualized by nature thinking beings may be, each
man still represents no more than an atom, or (if you prefer the
phrase) a very large molecule; in common with all the other similar
molecules, he forms a definite corpuscular system from which he
cannot escape.  Physically and biologically man, like everything else
that exists in nature, is essentially plural.  He is correctly
described as a &amp;lsquo;mass-phenomenon&amp;rsquo;.  This means that, broadly speaking,
we cannot reach our own ultimate without emerging from ourselves by
uniting ourselves with others, in such a way as to develop through
this union an added measure of consciousness — a process which
conforms to the great law of complexity.  Hence the insistence, the
deep surge, of love, which, in all its forms, drives us to associate
our individual center with other chosen and specially favored
centers: love, whose essential function and charm are that it
completes us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;em&gt;super-centration&lt;/em&gt;.  Although this is less obvious, it is
absolutely necessary to understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are to be fully ourselves, as I was saying, we find that we are
obliged to enlarge the base on which our being rests; in other words, we
have to add to ourselves something of &amp;rsquo;the Other&amp;rsquo;.  Once a small number
of centers of affection have been initiated (some special circumstances
determining their choice), this expansive movement knows no check.
Imperceptibly, and by degrees, it draws us into circles of
ever-increasing radius.  This is particularly noticeable in the world of
today.  From the very beginning, no doubt, man has been conscious of
belonging to one single great mankind.  It is only, however, for our
modern generations that this indistinct social sense is beginning to
take on its full and real meaning.  Throughout the last ten millennia
(which is the period which has brought the sudden speeding-up of
civilization) men have surrendered themselves, with but little
reflection, to the multiple forces (more profound than any war) which
were gradually bringing them into closer contact with one another; but
now our eyes are opening, and we are beginning to see two things.  The
first is that the closed surface of the earth is a constricting and
inelastic mold, within which, under the pressure of an ever-increasing
population and the tightening of economic links, we human beings are
already forming but one single body.  And the second thing is that
through the gradual building-up within that body of a uniform and
universal system of industry and science our thoughts are tending more
and more to function like the cells of one and the same brain.  This
must inevitably mean that as the transformation follows its natural line
of progress we can foresee the time when men will understand what it is,
animated by one single heart, to be united together in wanting, hoping
for, and loving the same things at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mankind of tomorrow is emerging from the mists of the future, and we
can actually see it taking shape: a &amp;lsquo;super-mankind&amp;rsquo;, much more
conscious, much more powerful, and much more unanimous than our own.
And at the same time (a point to which I shall return) we can detect an
underlying but deeply rooted feeling that if we are to reach the
ultimate of our own selves, we must do more than link our own being with
a handful of other beings selected from the thousands that surround us:
we must form one whole with all simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can draw but one conclusion from this twofold phenomenon which
operates both outside ourselves and inside ourselves: that what life
ultimately calls upon us to do in order that we may be, is to
incorporate ourselves into, and to subordinate ourselves to, an organic
totality of which, cosmically speaking, we are no more than conscious
particles.  Awaiting us is a center of a higher order — and already we
can distinguish it — not simply beside us, but &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;above&lt;/em&gt; us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must, then, do more than develop our own selves — more than give
ourselves to another who is our equal—we must surrender and attach our
lives to one who is greater than ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words: first, be.  Secondly, love.  Finally, worship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such are the natural phases of our personalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These, you must understand, are three linked steps in life&amp;rsquo;s upward
progress; and they are in consequence three superimposed stages of
happiness — if, as we have agreed, happiness is indissolubly associated
with the deliberate act of climbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The happiness of growing greater — of loving — of worshiping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking as our starting-point the laws of life, this, to put it in a
nutshell, is the triple beatitude which is theoretically foreseeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what is the verdict of experience on this point.  Let us for a
moment go directly to the facts, and use them to check the accuracy of
our deductions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there is the happiness of that deep-seated growth in one&amp;rsquo;s own
self — growth in capabilities, in sensibility, in self-possession.
Then, too, there is the happiness of union with one another, effected
between bodies and souls that are made to complete one another and come
together as one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have little need to emphasize the purity and intensity of these two
first forms of joy.  Everybody is in basic agreement on that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what shall we say about the happiness of sinking and losing self in
the future, in one greater than ourselves?&amp;hellip;  Is not this pure
theorizing or dreaming?  To find joy in what is out of scale with us, in
what we can as yet neither touch nor see.  Apart from a few visionaries,
is there anyone in the positivist and materialist world we are forced to
live in who can concern himself with such an idea?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who, indeed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, consider for a moment what is happening around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some months ago, at a similar meeting, I was telling you about two
Curies — the husband and wife who found happiness in embarking on a
venture, the discovery of radium, in which they realized that to lose
their life was to gain it.  Just think, then: how many other men (in a
more modest way, maybe, and in different forms and circumstances),
yesterday and today, have been possessed, or are still possessed, even
to the point of death, by the demon of research?  Try to count them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Arctic and Antarctic: Nansen, Andree, Shackleton, Charcot, and
any number of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The men of the great peaks: the climbers of Everest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laboratory workers who ran such risks: killed by rays or by the
substances they handled — victims of a self-injected disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add to these the legion of aviators who conquered the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And those, too, who shared man&amp;rsquo;s conquest of man: all who risked, or
indeed gave, their lives for an idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a rough count; and when you have done so, take the writings and
letters left by these men (such of them as left any), from the most
noteworthy of them (the everyday names) to the most humble (those whose
names are not even known) — the airmail pilots who twenty-five years ago
were pioneering the air-route across America for human thoughts and
loves, and paid for it, one after another, with their lives.  What do
you find when you read what they confided to paper?  You find joy, a joy
that is both higher and deeper — a joy full of power: the explosive joy
of a life that has at last found a &lt;em&gt;boundless&lt;/em&gt; area in which to expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joy, I repeat, in that which knows no bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What generally saps and poisons our happiness is that we feel that we
shall so soon exhaust and reach the end of whatever it is that attracts
us: we know the pain of separation, of loss by attrition — the agony of
seeing time fly past, the terror of knowing how fragile are the good
things we  hold, the disappointment of coming so soon to the end of what
we are and of what we love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when a man has found, in an ideal or a cause, the secret of
collaboration and self-identification (whether it be close or distant)
with the universe as it advances, then all those dark shadows disappear.
The joy of worshiping so spreads over the joy of being and the joy of
loving as to allow them to expand and grow firmer (Curie, for example,
and Termier were admirable friends, fathers and husbands): it does not
lessen or destroy the earlier joys, and it holds and brings with it, in
its fullness, a wonderful peace.  Its source of nourishment is
inexhaustible, because it gradually becomes one with the very
consummation of the world in which we move; by the same token, moreover,
it is safe from every threat of death and decay.  Finally, it is, in one
way or another, constantly within our reach, since the best way we have
of reaching it is simply, each one of us in his own place, to do what we
are able to do as well as we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joy of the element which has become conscious of the whole which it
serves and in which it finds fulfillment — the joy which the reflective
atom draws from awareness of its function and completion within the
universe which contains it — this, both logically and factually, is the
highest and most progressive form of happiness I can put before you and
hope that you may attain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;2-the-fundamental-rules-of-happiness&#34;&gt;2. THE FUNDAMENTAL RULES OF HAPPINESS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for pure theory.  We may now consider in what ways it can be
applied to our individual lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have just made it clear that true happiness is a happiness of growth
— and, as such, it awaits us in a quarter characterized by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unification of self within our own selves;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;union of our own being with other beings who are our equals;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subordination of our own life to a life which is greater than ours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What consequences do these definitions entail for our day-to-day
conduct?  And what practical action should we take in order to be happy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can, of course, satisfy your curiosity and assist your good will by
only the most general indications; for it is here that, quite rightly,
we come up against any number of problems of taste, accident and
temperament.  Life becomes established and progresses in nature and
structure only by reason of the very great variety of its elements.
Each one of us sees the world and makes his approach to it from a
particular angle, backed by a reserve of vital energy, with its own
peculiarities, which cannot be shared by others.  (We may note,
incidentally, that it is this complementary diversity which underlies
the biological value of &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo;.)  Each of us, therefore, is the
only person who can ultimately discover for himself the attitude, the
approach (which nobody else can imitate), which will make him cohere to
the utmost possible degree with the surrounding universe as it continues
its progress; that cohesion being, in fact, a state of peace which
brings happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bearing these reservations in mind, we can, following our earlier lines
of thought, draw up the following three rules of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are to be happy, we must first react against our tendency to
follow the line of least resistance, which causes us either to remain
as we are, or to look primarily to activities external to ourselves
for what will provide new impetus to our lives.  We must, it is true,
sink our roots deep into the rich, tangible, material realities which
surround us; but in the end it is by working to achieve our own inner
perfection — intellectual, artistic, moral — that we shall find
happiness.  The most important thing in life, Nansen used to say, is
to find oneself.  Through and beyond matter, spirit is hard at work,
building.  — &lt;em&gt;Centration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are to be happy we must, secondly, react against the
selfishness which causes us either to close in on ourselves, or to
force our domination upon others.  There is a way of loving — a bad
and sterile way — by which we try to possess rather than to give
ourselves.  Here again, in the case of the couple or the group, we
meet that same law of maximum effort which governed the progress of
our interior development.  The only love which brings true happiness
is that which is expressed in a spiritual progress effected in
common.  — &lt;em&gt;Decentration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we are to be happy — completely happy — we must, thirdly, in
one way or another, directly or through some medium which gradually
reaches out further afield (a line of research, a venture, an idea,
perhaps, or a cause), transfer the ultimate interest of our lives to
the advancement and success of the world we live in.  If we are to
reach the zone where the great permanent sources of joy are to be
found, we must be like the Curies, like Termier and Nansen, like the
first aviators and all the pioneers I spoke of earlier: we must
re-polarize our lives upon one greater than ourselves.  Do not be
afraid that this means that if we are to be happy we must perform
some remarkable feat or do something quite out of the ordinary; we
have only to do what any one of us is capable of: become conscious of
our living solidarity with the great Thing, and then do the smallest
thing in a great way.  We must add one stitch, no matter how small it
be, to the magnificent tapestry of life; we must discern the Immense
which is building up and whose magnetic pull is exerted at the very
heart of our own humblest activities and at their term; we must
discern it and cling to it — when all is said and done, that is the
great secret of happiness.  As one of the most acute, and most
materialist, thinkers of modern England, Bertrand Russell, has put
it: it is in a deep and instinctive union with the whole current of
life that the greatest of all joys is to be found.  —
&lt;em&gt;Super-centration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There you have the real core of what I have to say to you; but, having
reached that point, there is one more thing which I owe it to you and to
myself to say, if I am to be absolutely truthful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently reading a curious book (H. G. Wells, The Anatomy of
Frustration), in which the English novelist and thinker H. G. Wells
writes about the original views recorded earlier by an American
biologist and businessman, William Burrough Steele, which bear precisely
on the point we are now considering, human happiness. Steele tries, with
much good sense and cogency, to show (just as I have been doing) that
since happiness cannot be dissociated from some notion of immortality,
man cannot hope to be fully happy unless he sinks his own interests and
hopes in those of the world, and more particularly in those of mankind.
He adds, however, that, put in those terms, the solution is still
incomplete; for if we are to be able to make a complete gift of self we
must be able to love.  And how can one love a collective, impersonal
reality — a reality that in some respects must seem monstrous — such as
the world, or even mankind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objection which Steele found when he looked deeper, and to which
he gave no answer, is terribly and cruelly to the point.  My treatment
of the subject would, therefore, be both incomplete and disingenuous if
I did not point out to you that the undeniable movement which, as we can
see, is leading the mass of mankind to place itself at the service of
progress is not &amp;lsquo;self-sufficient&amp;rsquo;: if this terrestrial drive which I am
asking you to share is to be sustained, it must be harmonized and
synthesized with the Christian drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can look around and note how the mysticism of research and the social
mysticisms are advancing, with admirable faith, towards the conquest of
the future.  Yet no clearly defined summit, and, what is more serious,
no lovable object is there for them to worship.  That is the basic
reason why the enthusiasm and the devotion they arouse are hard, arid,
cold, and sad; to an observer they can only be a cause for anxiety, and
to those who aspire to them they can bring only an incomplete happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, parallel with these human mysticisms, and until now
only marginal to them, there is Christian mysticism; and for the last
two thousand years this has constantly been developing more profoundly
(though few realize this) its view of a personal God: a God who not only
creates but animates and gives totality to a universe which he gathers
to himself by means of all those forces which we group together under
the name of evolution.  Under the persistent pressure of Christian
thought, the infinitely distressing vastness of the world is gradually
converging upwards, to the point were it is transfigured into a focus of
loving energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely, then, we cannot fail to see that these two powerful currents
between which the force of man&amp;rsquo;s religious energies is divided — the
current of human progress, and the current of all embracing charity —
need but one thing, to run together, and complete one another?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose, first, that the youthful surge of human aspirations,
fantastically reinforced by our new concepts of time and space, of
matter and life, should make its way into the life-stream of
Christianity, enriching and invigorating it; and suppose at the same
time, too, that the wholly modern figure of a universal Christ, such as
is even now being developed by Christian consciousness, should stand,
should burst into sight, should spread its radiance, at the peak of our
dreams of progress, and so give them precision, humanize and personalize
them.  Would not this be an answer, or rather &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; complete answer, to
the difficulties before which our action hesitates?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless it receives a new blood transfusion from matter, Christian
spirituality may well lose its vigor and become lost in the clouds.
And, even more certainly, unless man&amp;rsquo;s sense of progress receives an
infusion from some principle of universal love, it may well turn away
with horror from the terrifying cosmic machine in which it finds itself
involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we join the head to the body — the base to the peak — then, suddenly,
there comes a surge of plenitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tell you the truth, I see the complete solution to the problem of
happiness in the direction of a Christian humanism: or, if you prefer
the phrase, in the direction of a super-human Christianity within which
every man will one day understand that, at all times and in all
circumstances, it is possible for him not only to serve (for serving is
not enough) but to cherish in all things (the most forbidding and
tedious, no less than the loveliest and most attractive) a universe
which, in its evolution, is charged with love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Managers Won't Let You Refactor</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/05/12/why-managers-wont-let-you-refactor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 07:42:54 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/05/12/why-managers-wont-let-you-refactor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you always wonder why managers won&amp;rsquo;t let you refactor, let us understand the
reasons behind the decision. As a software developer, one of the most common
frustrations is being denied the opportunity to refactor code. It&amp;rsquo;s a situation
many of us have faced, where we see the potential for improvement but are met
with resistance from managers and stakeholders. Understanding why this happens
can help us navigate these challenges and advocate for better code practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;refactoring-vs-redesign-clarifying-the-difference&#34;&gt;Refactoring vs. Redesign: Clarifying the Difference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refactoring is often misunderstood as a large-scale redesign, leading to
misconceptions about its risks and benefits. In reality, true refactoring
involves small, incremental improvements that enhance code readability,
maintainability, and extensibility.  It aligns with the &amp;ldquo;boy scout rule,&amp;rdquo; where
each change leaves the codebase in a better state than before, without
requiring explicit permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;addressing-stakeholder-concerns&#34;&gt;Addressing Stakeholder Concerns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managers and stakeholders may hesitate to approve refactoring due to concerns
about project timelines and potential disruptions. They prioritize delivering
critical functionalities and minimizing risks, which can overshadow the
long-term benefits of continuous code improvement. By demonstrating the value
of incremental refactoring in reducing technical debt and enhancing overall
project efficiency, developers can align stakeholders with the importance of
ongoing code maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;embracing-a-culture-of-continuous-improvement&#34;&gt;Embracing a Culture of Continuous Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than viewing refactoring as a one-time activity that requires formal
approval, fostering a culture of continuous improvement within the development
team can lead to organic, ongoing enhancements. By integrating small
refactorings into daily coding practices, developers can proactively address
code quality issues without disrupting project timelines or introducing
unnecessary risks. This approach not only improves the codebase iteratively but
also cultivates a shared responsibility for code quality among team members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-navigating-the-refactoring-dilemma&#34;&gt;Conclusion: Navigating the Refactoring Dilemma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you encounter resistance to refactoring, remember that the
reluctance is often rooted in valid concerns about project delivery and risk
management. By advocating for a culture of continuous improvement, emphasizing
the benefits of incremental refactoring, and aligning with stakeholder
priorities, developers can overcome barriers to code enhancement and drive
positive change within their teams.  Refactoring isn&amp;rsquo;t just about improving
code—it&amp;rsquo;s about fostering a mindset of ongoing improvement that benefits the
entire development process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Believing Is Seeing</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/05/09/believing-is-seeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 11:16:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/05/09/believing-is-seeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untutored minds are very prone to mistake inferences for observations, and
prepossessions for facts; their observations and their judgments are alike
vitiated by dogma and prejudice; they do not seek to investigate, they seek to
prove.  The old proverb is inverted, believing is seeing. The student of
science must pledge himself to do his best to eliminate prepossession and dogma
from his judgments, and he must spare no pains to acquire the habit of
recording phenomena as they are observed; and to distinguish sharply between
what is or has been actually seen, and what is mentally supplied. It requires a
mind disciplined like a soldier to avoid the natural inclination to look away
from unwelcome facts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Frederick Ludwig Hoffman&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advice From Kipchoge</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/03/17/advice-from-kipchoge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 12:00:33 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/03/17/advice-from-kipchoge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eliud_Kipchoge&#34;&gt;Eliud Kipchoge&lt;/a&gt;, one of the running greats, shared the following advice with
runners and others, on a podcast. Below, I present some of that guidance,
rephrased in my own language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you achieve something, celebrate. But soon start focusing on the next goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of focusing on success, focus on training and planning which can
bring success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not sit and wait for success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success is proof of your mastery over what you are doing. But you need a
system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define success in your own view.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running is life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life is about movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflect daily on whether you influenced the world positively or
negatively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pain is part of success. Learn to enjoy pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run daily, and do resistance training 3 days a week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of endurance training keeps injuries at bay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self discipline means sacrificing passions and pleasures in order to work
on your career.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No human is limited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believe it first before you can do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success is a process. It&amp;rsquo;s mantra is:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say no a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set your priorities right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid complaining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reaching Long Term Goals</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/03/13/reaching-long-term-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 11:14:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/03/13/reaching-long-term-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Reaching a goal or successfully executing a plan — one thing they have in
common is that they need us to make progress.  Our rate of success in
reaching the short term goals is a good indicator of whether we will
succeed at long term goals. This is because the one thing we need to do for
the short term goal — make progress in the present — is also applicable
to longer term goals but with an amplified effect on the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-we-fail&#34;&gt;Why we fail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, we are not very good at making progress &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. We think we could have
made progress in the past. We think we can definitely make progress in the
future. But we fail at making progress here and now. We are optimistic when
setting a goal. In the excitement of thinking about a positive future, we
believe we can do more than our track record would indicate. This is why we
come up with lofty new year goals only to be disappointed by our inability
to follow through with our plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-succeed&#34;&gt;How to succeed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are not reaching our short term goals, it is unlikely that we will
reach the long term goals. We should first fix this by improving our
success rate of reaching short term goals. This helps us get quick
feedback and allows us to test out strategies that do and do not work for
us. We can play with the two knobs that we control:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;our ability to finish the planned tasks of the day; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;setting realistic goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-daily-tasks&#34;&gt;The daily tasks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, when we plan the tasks for the next day, we are
optimistic. We tend to trust our future self to do things that our current
self may be unwilling to take on. Yet, we go ahead and plan the tasks for
tomorrow with the assumption that when the time comes, we will be up for
the tasks. When we see ourselves
constantly fall short on this metric, the first thing to do is improve the
day to day success rate of completed tasks, whatever they may be. This is
how we train ourselves to actually do those things that we said we will do.
This is a muscle that can and must be trained.  Every little success here
creates a positive feedback loop, and it further improves our success rate
of reaching short term goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;be-realistic&#34;&gt;Be realistic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While training our ability to complete the daily tasks, we should pay close
attention to how we feel as the days go by. It is possible to power through
our daily tasks for a few days and create a high success rate but if we
feel worse with each passing day, that pace is unsustainable. The pace
improves with time, but the optimal pace is highly individual and hence we
must be careful to not compare ourselves to others.  Once we hit a
sustainable pace, we can use that as an input when we plan for the long
term goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we are still failing to reach our short term goals, let us not assume
we will magically succeed in our long term goals. We should first train to
get better at reaching our short term goals.  This not only gives us a
realistic assessment of our current abilities, but when done frequently, it
also improves our abilities. This is the path to reaching our long term
goals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antidote to Distractions: Surf the Urge</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/02/19/antidote-to-distractions-surf-the-urge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 14:37:25 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2024/02/19/antidote-to-distractions-surf-the-urge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across a nice tip in the book &amp;ldquo;Indistractable: How To
Control Your Attention and Choose Your Life&amp;rdquo; by Nir Eyal.  The author
asserts that the solution to avoiding distractions is not to abstain from
the things that are distracting us but to identify the inner triggers that
lead to distraction and manage them instead. This is really powerful
because now we can no longer pin the blame for &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; distractions on
&lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distraction tricks us into prioritizing the urgent and easy over hard and
long term.  There are two kinds of triggers: external and internal.
According to the author, only 10% of the triggers are external but 90% are
internal!  Most distractions begin inside, and are usually caused by
boredom, fatigue, loneliness, anxiety, stress, etc.  And the root cause of
distractions is our inability to deal with these discomforts.  One tool to
avoid distraction is the 10 minute rule.  When you are on a task and the
urge for distraction strikes, do one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell yourself that you will scratch the urge but not yet. Get back to
the task for at least 10 minutes. Generally, the urge subsides and you
will be able to continue on your task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surf the urge. Literally sit and observe your urge but do not act on it
for at least 10 minutes. When we observe the urge, we soon learn that it
is like a wave and it subsides soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trick generally works. Definitely worth trying.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dead Tree Dictionary</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/03/16/dead-tree-dictionary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 12:16:20 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/03/16/dead-tree-dictionary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Growing up, with no computers around me, the only way to know the definition
of a new word was either to ask around or use a dictionary.  Things changed
with time and now &amp;mdash; for decades &amp;mdash; the fastest way to look up the meaning
of a word is to check online.  MacOS also provides a handy keyboard shortcut
&amp;mdash; CTRL + CMD + d to look up the word under the mouse pointer.  With time, my
reading habit has shifted away from the screen, to dead tree versions of
books, newspapers and news magazines.  This has reduced my general levels of
stress and anxiety, but I digress. This new shift presents a challenge when I
need to use a dictionary.  For a long time, I would pick up the phone, open
the dictionary app to look up the word.  But when I do that, I would often get
sucked into other things on the phone such as new emails, messages, and the
other app notifications would scream for attention.  By the time I realize
that I sidetracked, I would lose the original context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solution was to dust up the good old dead tree dictionary.  I have this
Merriam-Webster&amp;rsquo;s Collegiate Dictionary (Eleventh Edition) which I had bought
on an impulse, thinking that my children should know what a physical
dictionary looks like and should also learn how to use one.  They have used it
a few times but it sits on the shelf mostly unused.  Not any more.  Now I keep
this dictionary handy when I am reading, and do not hesitate to use it without
worrying about the &amp;ldquo;inefficiency&amp;rdquo; of using a physical dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do this? Well, I found a few benefits of using a physical dictionary.  I
don&amp;rsquo;t get sidetracked.  The longer it takes to look up a word also seems to
correlate positively with greater retention.  And finally, I am able to avoid
distractions while reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on a Roadshow Event</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/02/25/reflections-on-a-roadshow-event/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2023 10:24:17 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/02/25/reflections-on-a-roadshow-event/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I attended a roadshow by Google Cloud at the Novotel Hotel in Bellandur, Bengaluru. There were around two dozen attendees and a panel of six executives from some well-known companies. The panel discussion involved questions from the moderator, a Google employee, and they had said there would be time for audience questions at the end. Unfortunately, the panel discussion ran over time, and there was no opportunity for Q&amp;amp;A with the panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next part of the event involved introductions by the attendees and questions for the Google employees. The last hour was spent on dinner, drinks, and socializing. I was surprised by how much I enjoyed this part of the event (no, I did not drink). Since the start of Covid lockdowns, I have worked remotely and continue to do so to this day. Despite the advantages of remote work, one thing I miss is meeting with people to discuss industry trends and hear their perspectives on various topics. Yesterday, I got to do just that, and it was refreshing. I met a young startup founder, a product owner from a large company, a finance manager from another tech company, executives from F&amp;amp;G industry companies, and others. Most of them were just as eager to share their stories as I was to hear them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the experience, I realize I should seek out more networking opportunities like this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incident Management 101: Communicate, Solve, and Analyze</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/01/13/incident-management-101-communicate-solve-and-analyze/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 12:21:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/01/13/incident-management-101-communicate-solve-and-analyze/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the world of software development, incidents and issues happen all the time; sometimes major ones but mostly minor. Some companies have well-defined checklists and rulebooks for handling incidents, perhaps because they move fast and break things often. Others do not have a rulebook because incidents are a rarity, and they let people&amp;rsquo;s best judgment prevail in terms of how these incidents are handled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time you find yourself in the eye of a storm, remember these three principles of good incident management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicate: The moment you find yourself an owner of an incident, start communicating. Address your communication to everybody who should know. This could be via email, team chat, or whatever else your company uses to communicate broadly. Let people know about the nature of incident, what is your current understanding of the ongoing impact on business, and what are you planning to do next. Update this thread every time you have something important to say. If you get stuck and it is taking longer for you to make progress, make sure you communicate that too. The last thing you want is for the stakeholders to start pinging you directly for updates which will slow you down. The updates on the communication should stop only after the issue is resolved and your last update should include a summary of the fix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solve: Your goal during an incident is to find the best possible solution in the shortest amount of time, in order to minimize business impact. Seek help as soon as you need it, and make sure you are reaching out to those who you think are in the right position to be able to help you. If the ongoing impact is severe, and you are unable to make progress, escalate up your management chain to let them know that you will need help from someone more knowledgeable in a certain area. Let them find you someone who can step in and help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze: Once the storm is over, the next step is to dive deep to find out what caused the issue, what can be improved to prevent similar incidents in the future, and come up with a list of action items. The action you and your team will take after the incident will show the level of maturity of the team as well as the organization. Good teams always improve things in the aftermath of an incident. They focus more on learning and understanding the past mistakes and spend less or no time finger-pointing or blaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These simple steps can be followed even if your team or organization is not in the habit of expecting any of this from you. Use this as an opportunity to show your maturity and raise the team bar. This approach will help reduce the stress of incident management by putting you in a problem-solving mode. You and your team will emerge from the crisis much better, stronger, and with a deeper understaning of your applications and business.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming by Hand Will Remain Essential</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/01/10/programming-by-hand-will-remain-essential/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 10:22:44 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/01/10/programming-by-hand-will-remain-essential/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is why old-fashioned programming by hand will not go away after the onset of AI-assisted programming. Think of programming by hand,  unaided by AI, as something similar to walking. Walking is essential for getting us around and improving our health and general well-being. There is enough evidence (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://lithub.com/on-the-link-between-great-thinking-and-obsessive-walking/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/walking-helps-us-think&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) for how walking improves creativity in any field, including art, math, science, or business. But in terms of helping us get around, walking is perhaps our last choice. We don&amp;rsquo;t walk to work except for the lucky few who live within walking distance from their workplace. We don&amp;rsquo;t walk to a vacation destination. We don&amp;rsquo;t walk to a business conference across the country or across continents. Depending on the distance you need to go, you may choose anything from biking, driving, taking a train, or flying. Yet, walking remains indispensable and we should and we do walk when we can. Transportation tech is advancing every day but we will never forego the ability to walk just because there are faster and more comfortable alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, in the new world of AI-assisted programming, the good old unaided programing will remain an essential skill for software developers. They will be hired, assessed, promoted, rewarded etc. based on this skill. Please remember this next time you are worried about low-code, no-code, or AI-assisted programming replacing a good programmer. If you like programming, keep practicing because it is not going away. At least not in our lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rise of AI-Assisted Coding and Writing</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/01/09/the-rise-of-ai-assisted-coding-and-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 11:20:34 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2023/01/09/the-rise-of-ai-assisted-coding-and-writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I first heard of &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/&#34;&gt;OpenAI&lt;/a&gt; sometime in 2021 when their &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/dall-e-2/&#34;&gt;DALL·E&lt;/a&gt; model-based image generation and manipulation capabilities became publicly available. It created a stir in the tech circle as well as among artists. What pushed OpenAI into the mainstream discussion was their recent launch of &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt/&#34;&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt;, which has capabilities that most people can use, making it a game changer. The way it works is that you provide a prompt and it gives you an output based on that prompt. Students can prompt it to do their homework, journalists can prompt it to write news stories, software developers can prompt it to write code or generate comment for a code snippet, authors can prompt it to write books, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This capability is still in its infancy but has reached a point where it will soon change the way people work. It was quite tempting for me to have this post written by ChatGPT, but I resisted that temptation because I don&amp;rsquo;t want to take the fun out of writing a blog post. It would be too easy to churn out post after post using ChatGPT, but then what&amp;rsquo;s the point? We write in order to aid our thinking. However, I have already started using ChatGPT for writing in general, and so have millions of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/features/copilot&#34;&gt;GitHub Copilot&lt;/a&gt;, AI-assisted coding will gain momentum. Though Copilot started off getting some flack for copyright infringement, but once the dust settles, it will be a game changer. A few open-source alternatives are also in the making and will compete with Copilot. It is just a matter of time before enough software developers would have tried Copilot or equivalent, and they will be surprised by the difference it makes to their productivity. It will take care of writing all the boiler plate, and let you tweak and finetune the core or business logic it proposes. Eventually, the business leaders will expect software developers to deliver more and deliver faster. They will be able to cut cost by reducing the development team sizes or do more with the existing teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some software developers may initially see this as a threat, but this will instead have the effect of making tech more approachable or viable for businesses with smaller tech budgets. The net result will be more jobs in the tech sector. I think it is time for us to start thinking of AI-assisted coding and writing as tools in our toolkit. The future continues to get more exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning a Language</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2022/11/17/learning-a-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 13:20:34 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2022/11/17/learning-a-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.chalmers.se/~ulfp/Review/SStyle.pdf&#34;&gt;Steven Pinker on learning a language&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You learn a language by exposure. First during the critical stages of growing up, a process surprisingly fast and effective, but only pertaining to the basic aspect of language, namely its oral one. Similarly to learn to write you need to read a lot, and this is a far less natural process and takes much longer time. To acquire a sense of style you need a lot of exposure, and this is what eventually provides you with an ear going beyond that of the oral aspect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also makes sense if read in the context of programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Links: 13 July 2022</title>
      <link>https://karecha.com/blog/2022/07/13/three-good-links-13-july-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 08:46:53 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://karecha.com/blog/2022/07/13/three-good-links-13-july-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://slack.engineering/remote-development-at-slack/&#34;&gt;Remote Development at Slack&lt;/a&gt;: Slack&amp;rsquo;s developer productivity team moved the entire development experience to remote environments, from code intelligence to type-checking and builds. Engineers no longer have to maintain code or dependencies on their local laptops. They can get a fresh isolated environment on demand, ready to be used within a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jvns.ca/blog/2022/07/09/monitoring-small-web-services/&#34;&gt;Monitoring tiny web services&lt;/a&gt;: If you run a small but business critical website, this post is for you. Monitor your services with bare minimum cost and effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.honeycomb.io/blog/lies-my-parents-told-me-about-logs/&#34;&gt;Lies My Parents Told Me (About Logs)&lt;/a&gt;: Any time there are changes in your scale or maturity or environment, you may need to reconsider your assumptions about logs, and these are good enough place to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
